In this video, I'd like to start to talk about clustering.
이 비디오에서는, 클러스터 분석(클러스터링)에 대한 이야기부터 시작하겠습니다.
This will be exciting, because this is our first unsupervised learning algorithm,
이게 참 재밌을텐데요, 왜냐면 이건 우리가 라벨이 붙어 있지 않은 데이터로부터 배울
where we learn from unlabeled data instead from labelled data.
첫 번째 자율(unsupervised)학습 알고리즘이기 때문입니다.
So, what is unsupervised learning?
그럼, Unsupervised learning이란 무엇일까요
I briefly talked about unsupervised learning at the beginning of the class but
수업 처음에 간단히 자율학습에 대해서 설명했었는데요,
it's useful to contrast it with supervised learning.
지도(supervised)학습 알고리즘이랑 비교해 볼 수 있습니다.
So, here's a typical supervised learning problem where we're given
여기 전형적인 지도 학습 데이터가 주어졌다고 생각해 봅시다.
a labeled training set and the goal is to find the decision boundary that separates
최종 목표는 이 두 그룹의 경계선을 찾는 것이고
the positive label examples and the negative label examples.
각 데이터에는 o x라는 라벨이 붙어 있습니다.
So, the supervised learning problem in this case is given a set of labels to fit
지도 학습 문제에서는 이런 경우, 주어진 데이터를
a hypothesis to it.
어떤 가설에 맞추어 fitting합니다.
In contrast, in the unsupervised learning problem
반면에, 자율학습 문제에서는
we're given data that does not have any labels associated with it.
주어진 데이터에 o x같은 라벨이 안 붙어 있기 때문에
So, we're given data that looks like this.
데이터가 이런 식으로 보이게 됩니다.
Here's a set of points add in no labels, and so, our training set is
이렇게 라벨이 없는 데이터가 있으면 우리가 사용할 훈련 집합(training set)은
written just x1, x2, and so on up to x m and we don't get any labels y.
x(1), x(2), ... x(m)이라고 쓸 수 있고, 라벨 y는 정의되지 않았습니다.
And that's why the points plotted up on the figure don't have any labels with
그러므로 그림 속의 점들은 이렇게 라벨이
them.
표시되지 않았어요.
So, in unsupervised learning what we do is we give this sort of
그래서, 자율학습에서 우리가 해야 할 것은
unlabeled training set to an algorithm and
라벨이 없는 훈련 집합에 알고리즘을 부여하고
we just ask the algorithm find some structure in the data for us.
데이터가 가지고 있는 어떠한 구조를 그 알고리즘이 찾도록 하는 것입니다.
Given this data set one type of structure we might have an algorithm find is that it
알고리즘을 찾을 수 있다고 생각되는 구조의 예를 하나 보면, 이러한 데이터 집합이 주어졌을 때
looks like this data set has points grouped into two separate clusters and
이 데이터들은 두 개의 분리된 클러스터로 구성되어 있는 것 같이 보이고
so an algorithm that finds
그래서 알고리즘은 지금 제가 원을 그린 것 같은
clusters like the ones I've just circled is called a clustering algorithm.
클러스터를 찾게 됩니다. 이게 바로 '클러스터링 알고리즘'입니다.
And this would be our first type of unsupervised learning,
그리고 이 '클러스터링'이 바로 우리가 처음으로 배울 자율학습의 예제입니다.
although there will be other types of unsupervised learning algorithms that
나중에 배우겠지만 다른 종류의 자율학습 예제도 많이 있는데요,
we'll talk about later that finds other types of structure or
데이터 속에서 클러스터가 아닌 다른 타입의 구조를 찾거나,
other types of patterns in the data other than clusters.
다른 종류의 패턴을 찾거나 하는 것들입니다.
We'll talk about this after we've talked about clustering.
일단 클러스터링에 대하여 이야기한 후에 다른 걸로 넘어가겠습니다.
So, what is clustering good for?
그럼, 클러스터링은 어떤 경우에 적합할까요?
Early in this class I already mentioned a few applications.
예전 수업에서 이미 몇 가지 예를 언급했었습니다.
One is market segmentation where you may have a database of customers and
첫 번째로 시장을 세분화해 마케팅 전략을 세울 때, 고객의 데이터베이스를 가지고
want to group them into different marker segments so
고객을 서로 다른 몇 개의 그룹으로 분류한다면
you can sell to them separately or serve your different market segments better.
각각의 그룹에게 다른 물품을 판매하거나 다른 서비스를 할 수 있습니다.
Social network analysis.
소셜 네트워크 분석을
There are actually groups have done this things like looking at
하고 있는 사람들은, 예를 들어,
a group of people's social networks.
사람들의 소셜 네트워크를 조사합니다.
So, things like Facebook, Google+, or maybe information
즉, 페이스북이나 Google+ 같은 SNS, 혹은
about who other people that you email the most frequently and who are the people
사람들이 이메일을 자주 주고받는 대상에 관한 정보를 보고
that they email the most frequently and to find coherence in groups of people.
그룹 속에서 일관성을 찾습니다.
So, this would be another maybe clustering algorithm where you know want to find who
소셜 네트워크 안에서 어떤 사람들이 같은 그룹에 있는지 찾고 싶은 것도
are the coherent groups of friends in the social network?
클러스터링 알고리즘이라고 할 수 있겠죠.
Here's something that one of my friends actually worked on which is, use
또 제 친구 하나가 실제로 일하고 있는 분야에서는,
clustering to organize computer clusters or to organize data centers better.
클러스터링을 사용해 컴퓨터 클러스터를 구성하거나 데이터 센터를 체계화할 수 있습니다.
Because if you know which computers in the data center in the cluster tend to work
왜냐하면 만약 데이터 센터 안의 어느 컴퓨터 클러스터가 서로 함께 일하려 하는지
together, you can use that to reorganize your resources and
알 수 있다면, 그걸 이용해 리소스를 재편성하거나,
how you layout the network and how you design your data center communications.
네트워크를 나열하거나, 데이터 센터의 커뮤니케이션을 디자인할 때 활용할 수 있기 때문입니다.
And lastly, something that actually another friend worked on using
그리고 마지막으로, 이건 다른 친구가 하는 일인데요,
clustering algorithms to understand galaxy formation and
클러스터링 알고리즘을 사용해서 은하의 형성을 이해, 즉,
using that to understand astronomical data.
천문학 데이터를 이해할 수 있습니다.
So, that's clustering which is our first example of an unsupervised
정리하면, 이런 것들이 자율 학습 알고리즘의
learning algorithm.
첫 번째 예로 배울 '클러스터 분석'입니다.
In the next video we'll start to talk about a specific clustering algorithm.
다음 비디오에서는 몇몇 구체적인 클러스터링 알고리즘에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.